Shouldn't
be there somewhere.
Yeah. She didn't need to do that.
No.
Another policy failure.
Yeah, no, that's wrong. That's not right.
It was completely 100%-
To
start,
because we have limited time. So, we're back into public
submissions on the Conservation Amendment Bill, and our first
submitter this afternoon is Forest and Bird.
Welcome to the select committee. We're looking forward to your
submission. We have 15 minutes with you, so we'll hand it over to you
to open up, but take your submission as read, and then we'll open up for
questions. So over to you.
Thank you. Tena koutou katoa. Thank you, Chair and committee members
for the opportunity to appear today. My name's Erika Tolman. I'm the acting CE.
With me is Richard Kape, GM Policy and Advocacy, and online
is Tim Williams, our senior environmental lawyer.
As most of you know, Forest and Bird is New Zealand's largest independent
conservation organization. For more than 100 years, we've worked across New
Zealand's unique natural heritage.
We represent New Zealanders from across the motu.
And our history includes the founding and development of New Zealand's
conservation system, including the part we played in the
establishment of the current Conservation Act.
So before turning to the detail of our submission, I want to make Forest and Bird's
overall position clear. If this bill cannot be fixed,
particularly proposed Section 6EA and its counterparts,
the visitor amenity areas, and the conservation planning processes, this
bill should not proceed.
While we recognize the need for some reform to ease DOC's administrative
burden, reform cannot proceed on the basis set out in this bill.
Unless significant changes are made, Forest and Bird says this bill should be
binned.
So,
the Conservation Act exists because Parliament recognized that public conservation
land needs a clear legal framework focused on protection.
That framework is not anti-tourism or necessarily anti-use.
It already allows appropriate use where it's consistent with conservation.
But it's not an economic development statute, and DOC should not be turned into an
economic development agency.
Conservation land and the nature within it is already under considerable pressure.
Native biodiversity continues to decline.
Thousands of species are threatened or at risk, and many
ecosystems are still deteriorating.
It would be unthinkable and wrong in that context to weaken the legal framework
that protects the places those species depend on.
Now, New Zealanders have made clear that public conservation land should not be
sold, swapped, or opened up for development.
Strong conservation safeguards and conservation supremacy must remain central
to our approach.
I want to acknowledge the government's commitment to removing the exchange and
disposal provisions from the bill,
and to retain the existing provisions in the Conservation Act, so that conservation
land will not be opened up for disposal unless the land has no or low
conservation values.
But to maintain that current approach to exchange and disposal under the Act,
the government will also need to fix the economic use and development provisions,
and to remove the backdoor for conservation land disposal in the Fast Track
Act.
So, we're going to cover four key matters in our remarks today,
and I'll start off with proposed Section 6EA and its counterparts.
So, our most significant concern,
is the proposed Section 6EA, together with the equivalent references in
the proposed purpose provisions for the NCPS in Section
13D,
for area plans, Section 13H, and concessions, Section
141.
As drafted, that section would require DOC to recognize economic
opportunities and enable economic use and development of public conservation land
to the greatest extent practicable.
The problem is not that economic activity happens on conservation land.
It already does. The problem is making economic development a
statutory objective in its own right, rather than something that's only allowed
where it's consistent with conservation.
So it's not a small administrative change.
It is a fundamental change that would change the legal starting point for all
future decisions under the Act. It would materially change conservation in
New Zealand.
It would also make disposal of public conservation land easier in both the
declassification decisions and exchange decisions.
It would make it easier for mining on PCL to happen.
So our strongly preferred position is that 6 A is deleted.
However, if the committee would like to
include it, we've included wording in our submission for it to be
amended.
And I'd just reiterate that it's not just 6 A, that it does feature in
several other parts of the bill.
Turning then to the backdoor Fast Track Approvals Act
process.
So I want to make it really clear today that even if the exchange and dispose
provisions are removed from the bill, the protection for
conservation land that New Zealanders have demanded will not be achieved unless the
Fast Track Act is also changed.
The reason is straightforward. The Fast Track Act creates a pathway for
disposal by exchange of large amounts of public conservation land,
which is the same outcome that New Zealanders loudly opposed earlier this year.
So first off, the Fast Track Act roughly doubles the amount of land available for
disposal by exchange. So under the Conservation Act currently, it's
only stewardship land is potentially available.
Under the Fast Track Act, a much broader range of conservation land
classifications is available other than very highly protected
land like the national parks.
Secondly, under the Fast Track
Act, its own test is included for exchanges.
So it's different from the Conservation Act test, and it's much less protective.
And part of that is that the environmental values of the exchange land don't need
to reflect a net gain for biodiversity, because money that
DOC gets as part of the exchange can also be considered in the weighing up.
So New Zealanders have made their feelings clear that conservation land should not
be disposed of, and fixing this bill alone will not address those concerns.
The Fast Track Approvals Act must also be amended so that the
regime is subject to the status quo measures under the Conservation Act that the
government has promised to preserve.
So this is available to the committee, that this bill already
makes changes to the Fast Track Approvals Act, and we've set out in
our submission the exact changes that are needed that the government can make good
on its promise in respect to conservation land.
Turning now to exchange and disposal.
So while the government has made a commitment to remove those provisions,
which we support, we are aware that there's still a wish to be able to
address what the minister has called bits and bobs.
As we've said repeatedly, when discussing the likes of the offsite
MetService building, we are not outright opposed to the sale or
exchange of conservation land where the land has no or very low
conservation value.
But we say that before designing any mechanism to dispose of
conservation land, we have to be really clear on what the policy problem is that
we're trying to solve and not rely on anecdotes.
We have not seen that clear problem statement set out.
We're very willing to work with ministers and the department,
once that statement is made really clear.
If any changes are needed
to those provisions, they must be very tightly designed.
Only land with no or very low conservation value should be considered.
Conservation values must be assessed robustly, and approval should be
recommended through an independent mechanism, such as the NZCA,
rather than left to broad ministerial discretion.
I'll pass now to my colleague, Richard.
Thanks, Erica. Kia ora, everybody. It's nice to see you all again.
There's several other points that might not have received the same amount of
attention as, say, disposals or 6 A economic development, but which
are actually really significant, and I think it's important to briefly put those
before the committee. So the first thing I really want to reiterate is that
stewardship land is conservation land.
That is how it is categorized under law.
So the assessment and reclassification process for stewardship land
must be completed so that the conservation values of those
lands are properly protected and genuinely low-value
lands can be dealt with transparency.
As a very live and real example, I would draw your attention to
the very threat that exists just now around one of New Zealand's
national treasures, the Denniston Plateau.
Mm.
The Denniston Plateau should be a scientific reserve.
The evidence is very clear that that is the status that it should
hold. That would make it protected under Schedule 4,
and it would not be possible to mine that.
Instead, New Zealand faces the very real prospect of
that wonderful place being ripped apart for an opencast coal
mine.
This needs to be addressed as a matter of urgency.
The other thing that I think we need to think about in the context of this bill is
the centralization of power.
We are in favor of administrative processes being streamlined, but I think
as we've seen around the Fast Track Act and many of the discussions that are
happening very live just now, whether it's in Orewa, Pegasus,
Fernhill, Arrowtown, Devonport, New Zealanders
want their local voices heard.
So taking local voices and independent checks out of the conservation
system is something that we strongly oppose.
Government should retain meaningful decision-making and the oversight roles
of conservation boards and the New Zealand Conservation Authority
rather than reducing them to be advisory bodies.
Ministerial powers need to be constrained, and they should be
constrained by clear statutory criteria and conservation
purposes.
That avoids political flip-flopping,
decision-making
made in political cycles, and therefore provides certainty and
clarity not only to the conservation system, but to
businesses and commercial operators who want to operate within
conservation
With regards visitor amenity areas, better visitor infrastructure
may be appropriate, but the current provisions in this bill are too
permissive. They risk undermining the very reasons, the very
values, why people come to these places in the first place.
Government should strengthen the test that amenities could not be
located reasonably outside
conservation land, and make this a key consideration.
So why are we looking to locate these amenities in the conservation land when we
could actually be supporting regional economies and local
towns by requiring that those amenities are located in those
spaces? There is a missed opportunity here.
On concessions and the National Conservation Policy Statement,
DOC is currently consulting on a draft of the first of these policy statements.
The proposed economic use and development provisions in this
bill have actually resulted in that draft, which is inconsistent with the
Conservation Act, and any concessions framework needs to be
consistent with conservation. The draft NCS would
attempt to, for example, deem hydro schemes as being consistent
with the purposes for which conservation parks are held.
That's wrong,
and it would create clear conflicts and inefficiencies for DOC
processes instead of actually achieving the ambition of this bill,
which is modernization and streamlining.
Government should remove the economic development objective and function from the
bill, ensure that the new planning framework for conservation
has conservation as its clear primary purpose.
So the NCPS was launched in parallel with this bill, and I think the intention
was to enable people to be able to read them side by side.
The unfortunate consequence of that is because of the significant flaws in this
bill, the NCPS now needs to be withdrawn and rewritten.
So it's significantly flawed, and actually the interaction of the two means that we
need to start again on the NCPS.
Finally, we'd ask the committee not to weaken the existing treaty
obligations or reduce the formal channels through which tangata whenua
perspectives are brought into conservation planning.
And you shouldn't look to weaken Section 4 or existing treaty obligations.
I think we're seeing the incredible value that mana whenua are bringing to
understanding conservation of place,
and removing those contributions would be a very bad move.
Look, finally, I note we are not opposed in principle to reasonable access
charges. So charging international visitors
to access the conservation estate, we don't have a problem with.
But I think we've also got to be clear, it would be additional to DOC's core
funding, and there should be transparency dedicated to conservation,
visitor infrastructure, biodiversity, and heritage outcomes.
I think in making that point, I think Forest and Bird is acutely aware that you may
be-- one of the main arguments that we've heard is that we need to generate more
revenue for conservation land.
And we think appropriate revenue tools can be part of the
solution, but you don't redefine the purpose of the conservation
estate in order to do that.
I think it's also important to point out just how much value the conservation
estate already delivers to New Zealanders, and we heard this
in that outpouring of aroha and that outpouring of emotion from
so many people across the country when we produced those maps.
The amount of return that we get from the conservation estate
massively outweighs the meager funding it receives.
So we know tourism alone is worth $19
billion to New Zealand this year, and the tourists do not come here for
our shopping malls.
There are also funding choices that we can make.
Government is currently spending $100 million of taxpayers'
money on supporting mining companies and another $200
million of taxpayer money for fossil fuel exploration.
That is $300 million, or 40% of
DOC's annual budget. There are choices that we can
make.
So just round off our comments, um-
You actually have about a minute for questions, so just-
Okay. I will say no more.
And we have got questions, and members, if we can keep them tight.
So, Priyanka.
Yes. Okay, so
this is about enabling more economic development on public conservation
land. You've talked about the removal of the sale and exchange clauses from the
bill and ensuring that the primary objective of DOC remains
conservation.
Is that enough to protect public conservation land?
No, quite frankly, and Forest and Bird
really grappled with should we advocate for getting rid of this whole bill,
because there are serious problems with it.
However, we do recognize that DOC needs to relieve their burden, so we
are not quite at the point of saying bin the bill yet,
on the proviso that these changes that we've set out, as well as the changes to the
Fast-track Approvals Act, can be made.
Thank you. Grant?
Yeah, and carrying on, on that theme around economic development.
So how do you address the issue that came up when Cathedral Cove was shut for
nearly two years? The local businesses in Hahei
basically lost all-- their patronage went down.
They really, really struggled.
Mm-hmm.
And DOC basically said, "Well, it's not our job to worry about the local
economy." How do you balance that given the
reason they were coming there was to go across to Cathedral Cove?
Excuse me, my nose is running.
Oh.
Carry on. Yes, please.
So I'm happy to talk to this one. So again, that goes back to my point there.
So we're defunding DOC. So DOC's budget is being cut year on year, and
it's got a massive budget shortfall forecast for the next few years.
But as you said, Grant, the amount of value that DOC delivers
to our local communities, to our country, and our economy as a whole is
significant. Part of the reason that I imagine it was saying that we can't do this
is it didn't have the money.
Mm-hmm.
So if you actually fund DOC properly- Then actually its ability to
support and expand that kind of local
economic benefits is there. But you do not need to change that act in order to do
that. You just need to get those funding settings right.
Okay. Thank you. One last question.
I wanted to pick up, there's so much in here, particularly about the
ministerial boards. What would be your main
concerns about that change from the conservation boards in
particular, and the New Zealand Conservation Authority to
ministers? What's your main concerns with that?
Tim, do you want to answer that one?
Sure. I think it's probably the point that Richard already made,
which is that it's really important to be able to have a consistent
conservation focused approach to this, and when you put
too much power in the hands of the ministers, it just results in
shorter term decision making and, essentially decision making
that isn't
focused on conservation. So, having independent expert
bodies that can
direct actions towards the purpose of the act is a really
important feature.
Look, thank you very much. We have gone over time, but look, we
do really respect the work that you put onto this, all the valuable feedback that
you're giving us, and we really appreciate that. So thank you very much.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
We now call upon our next submitter, who is
Tourism Industry Aotearoa.
Thank you.
Welcome to the select committee this afternoon.
You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll pass it over to you to make your
introductions.
Thank you.
And then open up for questions. Thank you.
Kia ora chair and committee. Thank you very much for inviting Tourism
Industry Aotearoa to submit for you in person today.
I am Rebecca Ingram, the chief executive of Tourism Industry Aotearoa.
We have approximately 1,200 tourism businesses who are our members.
That stretches from everything from Kapiti Island Nature Tours through
to Air New Zealand.
Tourism and conservation are deeply connected.
New Zealand's natural environment is the foundation of many visitors'
experiences, and tourism operators have a strong
interest in tourism and conservation working well together,
and conservation being protected and enhanced.
Retaining the status quo is not our preferred option.
We strongly support the direction of the reform.
Our submission is about getting the system settings
right.
There are three areas I would like to focus on today.
Our first concern is the proposed function requiring
the department
to enable use and development to the greatest extent.
We think the wording in the bill goes too far.
It potentially creates uncertainty about whether economic
development is being elevated above conservation outcomes.
Our preferred wording is simple. DOC should enable use and
development to the extent consistent with conservation.
Making this change will give DOC a clear and positive mandate to
recognize and enable appropriate economic
development and tourism opportunities while
establishing a clear conservation boundary.
This balance is something the legislation must strike.
With regard to concessions and investment certainty, TIA
strongly supports the intent of modernizing concessions.
Our comments relate to concession system, both in terms
of how the concessions are granted and how competitive allocation
will work.
For a tourism operator, a concession is often the cornerstone
of their business.
It allows them to invest in facilities, people and
systems.
Many concessionaires have spent decades developing
operations around particular places, and are genuine
partners in conservation efforts.
They invest in predator control, restoration projects,
visitor education, yet the current framework can feel
more transactional than collaborative.
Here is an example of how the current system can play out for a tourism
business.
We have a TIA member that has been operating
responsibly on PCL for almost 40 years,
including making a significant contribution to conservation.
Following the process outlined by DOC, they applied to renew their concession when
it was due to expire in 2023.
DOC initially offered a concession that in some cases
reduced their allocation by over 90%,
completely devaluing their business.
It then took two and a half years to prove
their case, which highlighted inconsistencies in
interpretation of planning documents, and the allocation of
concessions to other operators. They were finally granted
their satisfactory concession in June this year.
While individuals within the department, and I want to make this clearly, were
genuinely sympathetic and helpful,
they were at the mercy of a broken system
that was disempowering businesses and frustrating DOC.
For this reason, gains around efficiency,
statutory time frames, and improvements to granting
processes are very much supported.
With regard to competitive allocation, we acknowledge that competition may
be entirely appropriate in some circumstances
But operators need clarity about when competitive allocation might
occur, how existing investment and conservation
contributions will be recognised.
That certainty is critical to continued investment and
visitor experiences on conservation land, and we therefore ask
the committee to recommend greater clarity in the bill around
competitive allocation.
We have similar feedback around pre-approved concessions.
We support the principle. Removing unnecessary
bureaucracy for straightforward, low impact activities does
make sense, but the design needs appropriate safeguards.
In particular, the 12 month approval may be too
short to justify meaningful investment in
staff, equipment, safety systems, and product quality.
There's a risk that a mechanism designed to make the system easier
could inadvertently favor short term, low investment
operators over businesses committed to a place for a long
time. There are also questions around cumulative effect,
carrying capacity, and how pre-approved activities
will interact with existing concessionaires.
My third area of focus is the proposed international visitor access levy.
Tia supports the principles, but our support comes with
some conditions.
First, the revenue should be additional to existing DOC funding.
It should not simply substitute Crown funding.
Oh.
Second, we believe there should be a very strong connection between where
the money is raised and the place that it's collected.
Mm-hmm.
So if a visitor is being charged for access to a place, they should be able to
see their contribution improving conservation and the visitor experience
at place.
And third, implementation needs to consider how tourism is
sold.
Our submission therefore recommends at least 18 months notice before a
new access charge takes effect, so operators can incorporate it
into their pricing and international contracts if needed.
We also need to consider the cumulative cost to the visitor rather than
looking at each charge in isolation.
An international visitor already pays, many of them, $100 in the international
visitor levy. They may also face parking charges,
and costs passed through from other concessionaires.
An additional access charge needs to be considered as part of the
overall visitor experience.
Finally,
excuse me.
Many of the practical effects of this legislation will be determined by the policy
statement, area plans, and visitor amenity areas, and
through future regulations.
We support tourism and recreation being explicitly recognized
within the new planning framework.
Not every operational detail should be in primary
legislation, but Parliament does need to establish the important
principles and guardrails now.
We also think appropriate scrutiny and recommendation roles remain
important, particularly given the greater concentration of
decision making authority proposed within the bill.
Tia strongly supports modernization of the conservation system.
Mm-hmm.
We want a system that's easier to navigate, provides certainty,
encourages responsible investment,
and enables tourism to contribute more to conservation.
This bill should proceed with changes.
Three things are fundamental. Conservation must remain the
overriding purpose while enabling economic development.
The concession system must provide sufficient certainty
to encourage long-term investment,
and the new powers, planning processes, and visitor charging
mechanisms need some statutory guardrails.
With those settings right, we believe this bill can
deliver better outcomes for conservation, visitors,
tourism businesses, and New Zealand. Thank you.
I welcome your questions.
Oh. Thank you. Very useful information.
Priyanka?
Thank you for that.
You shared an example of-
Yes
... a member who had their concession,
renewed but their allocation cut by a significant amount.
Took a long time to get reinstated.
You made the point that DOC staff were willing
to, were sympathetic to the cause.
You kind of put it down to time frames, I think, in the existing
legislation. I'm assuming there's more to it than that.
Would you be able to expand on what
led to that situation-
Mm-hmm
... in existing leg versus how the proposed changes would
alleviate that?
Sure. So that is an example.
What the existing framework does is it has multiple layers of structures
that need to be applied in order for a concession to be delivered.
So you've got conservation management plans, conservation boards.
They are sometimes out of date. They haven't recognized
what's happening at a place today, and they're all laddering up to a piece of
legislation that's almost 40 years old.
Yeah.
And so the streamlining
that will exist in here for concessions in particular will enable
DOC to
approach standard concessions, and also those concessions
where they are with a reputable, well-known
established tourism operator to be recognized.
And so the challenge we've got in the way that it works currently is that there's
no certainty or consistency in the way that it's applied.
And so that's what we're hoping to change through this
modernization of the legislation.
Thank you. Look, I'm going to go to Rachel online because she didn't get a
question before and had her hand up. There you go, Rachel.
Hey. Thank you. Thank you. Hello, everyone.
Hello.
Rob Kneeden here. Hey, um
Your experience with the visitor levy, and it's obviously
gone up substantially,
but our observation is, well, some of us haven't seen
that really go into conservation or tourism
uses. Instead, it's been used for some other things like
advertising to Australia.
If it went up further,
do you have ideas of how it could be constrained so that it was actually used on
tourism infrastructure and conservation?
Sure. So the international visitor levy at $100 per person for
most international visitors coming into the country is split in two.
Our position on the IVL is that it should be used
100% for incremental gain and not be used as a substitution for
Crown funding.
Yeah.
The way in which it is then invested by DOC and through tourism
really needs to go into tourism-related infrastructure, amenities.
From a department perspective, it's about making sure that the
visitor experience and tourism-related assets that they're responsible for
can be kept
and advanced, that they're safe, that they can respond
to being put right when climate change will have an
effect on them.
Mm.
So
we think that's why it's really important to consider the role of the international
visitor levy alongside any new access charges together.
So this sort of holistic view. It's also why we believe
it's incredibly important that there are quite specific parameters
around any new access-related fees in this piece of
legislation. It's why we want to see if a new fee is
introduced, that it will be used at the place where it is being
raised.
Mm.
And what supplementary just on that, what do you imagine?
Can you just give some color to what you're saying about amenity and the
tourism facilities that might be needed? Are you talking toilets?
What are we talking about?
So at the high visitation sites that we're talking about,
I think it's about making sure we've got the core infrastructure in place, that
there's appropriate roading, parking,
that the bridges are being well-maintained and looked after, that the tracks are up
to spec. And that's not just for international visitors.
Anyone who is going to visit those sites will benefit from ensuring that that is
well looked after.
Then in some places, I think, it's about how we can
further enhance those places
in a way that delivers more in the visitor experience.
So for example, how are we partnering with iwi in specific locations
to make sure we're telling appropriate stories of those places?
Mm.
How are we connecting our visitors to conservation outcomes at those places, and
the difference they might be making through the contribution of their access levy?
So, I think that's important.
Look, I've just got a quick question that I wanted to jump in with, because it
comes back to 6 , which we've spoken about with lots of submitters.
But earlier we had RealNZ, they spoke about tourism being
included within that definition. You haven't said that.
Is there a reason you feel it captures tourism
with the wording that you're
saying here?
Sure. So,
we are suggesting that it changes in the way it's written.
We think the greatest extent is too far.
We think with other changes,
as identified in our submission, that that purpose statement would be
effective.
If we can't achieve some of the concession gains, for example, then I
think tourism may need to be more clearly articulated.
Okay. Yeah, no, that's great. And just one last quick question, Celia.
Oh, thank you very much, and thank you, Rachel, for asking one of my questions in a
great answer. I was interested in who you think
should be required to pay the visitor access
levy.
Mm-hmm.
Given the IVL doesn't apply to Australians
and certain other categories-
Mm-hmm
... do you think it should be all nationalities?
And then another submission talked about if people are
on working holidays and/or they're doing conservation work and so on,
should they have some kind of
concessional allowance?
Mm-hmm.
So as proposed, any international visitor would be
paying the access levy for a place that they're choosing to
frequent or go to, and we think that is appropriate.
There will need to be some definitions, though.
So for example, a number of tourism businesses might have a working holiday visa
holder from overseas who's working in their business for the summer.
Mm-hmm.
We would want them to be exempt, for example.
That's just a really practical example.
I think what matters a lot is that the international visitors that are being
asked to pay the levy can see how it turns up in their experience.
Mm.
That the toilets are good quality, and they're being looked after.
The tracks are well constructed. I think that's essential.
Thank you very much. We have met time.
We appreciate your time today-
Thank you
... that really thorough submission, so thank you.
Thank you.
It's great.
So we now move to our next submitter, Recreation
Aotearoa. Welcome to the select committee this afternoon.
You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand over to you to make your introductions
and then open for questions.
Very good. Tena koutou, Madam Chair and members of the committee.
Thank you for the opportunity to be here to speak to you today.
My name is Sarah Murray, and I'm the Chief Executive of Recreation Aotearoa.
We are an industry body and professional association for recreation
providers across New Zealand, and our mission is Ti Whai Oranga,
enhancing wellbeing through recreation.
And we believe that recreation is not a discretionary nice to have,
it's a fundamental component of New Zealand's physical and mental health, social
cohesion, youth development, and national identity.
Central government, through the Department of Conservation, is the largest provider
of outdoor recreation opportunities in New Zealand.
Every year, 80% of us visit public conservation lands
to walk, tramp, climb, bike, swim, paddle, and enjoy
a range of other recreation activities that help us connect with nature
The public conservation estate is New Zealand's largest recreation
infrastructure network, and as such, DOC plays a critical role in
ensuring New Zealanders can access quality outdoor recreation
opportunities and connect with our natural environment.
Recreation Aotearoa supports the bill's goal of modernising conservation
management. We recognize that parts of the current system are complex,
slow, and resource intensive. We support efforts to streamline
planning processes, improve concessions administration, and provide
greater consistency across the conservation estate.
We also support proposals to create a national conservation policy statement and
introduce area plans, noting that these,
we believe, need significant amendments as per our submission on
the NCPS.
What we don't support are reforms that would alter the
fundamental purpose of the Conservation Act or the Department of Conservation's
role.
The conservation system must be able to respond to changing visitor
expectations, increasing participation in outdoor recreation,
growing tourism, and the impacts of climate change.
It must also uphold the Crown's obligations under Te Tiriti o Waitangi
and actively support mana whenua to exercise kaitiakitanga.
But modernization of the legislation should improve how the system works,
not change why it exists. As currently drafted, the
bill shifts the longstanding statutory balance within New Zealand's conservation
framework. It fundamentally changes the purpose of conservation
land.
We strongly oppose the so-called economic clauses, specifically
the inclusion of the words "enabling economic activity to the greatest extent
practicable" as a key function of the Department of Conservation
and as a key purpose of the proposed NCPS area plans and
concessions framework.
We acknowledge that economic activity occurs on public conservation land.
We're not opposed to this. We support well-managed tourism, and we
recognize the important role concessionaires play in helping New Zealanders and
visitors access and enjoy public conservation lands.
But conservation of our shared natural and historic heritage must
remain the primary and overriding purpose of public conservation land,
and recreation must continue to be recognized and fostered as a core
public benefit, with economic activity enabled only where it
is consistent with conservation and recreation outcomes.
As such, we urge the committee to recommend that the existing hierarchy within the
act is preserved and that all references to economic activity are
qualified with a clear statement requiring consistency with
conservation outcomes.
Our next point is where we believe the committee has the greatest
opportunity to make a practical and meaningful improvement to the
bill, and that's around the current treatment of not-for-profit outdoor
education providers under the concessions regime.
The way that these providers are currently treated is inequitable and
inconsistent. At present, and rightly so, schools can
take students onto public conservation land without requiring a concession or
incurring the costs and administrative challenges that come with this.
However, not-for-profit outdoor education providers delivering the same
activities to the same students and tertiary
institutions who are training our future recreation, conservation,
tourism, and outdoor education workforce, they are required to hold a
concession. The activities are the same, the students are the
same, the public good, the public benefit is the same, only the
provider differs. In our view, that makes little sense.
Outdoor education is an integral part of New Zealand's education system.
Going on a school camp, doing your first overnight tramp, crossing a
river, visiting a national park for the first time, these are rites
of passage for young people in New Zealand.
They're the experiences that help us build resilience, they
teach leadership and teamwork, and they build environmental awareness, and
oftentimes, they help us develop our sense of identity.
Outdoor education connects young people with the natural environment, and it
fosters a lifelong love of conservation and recreation.
The public conservation estate is also New Zealand's greatest outdoor
classroom.
And these days, outdoor education activities are often delivered
by specialist outdoor education providers, the vast majority of
which are charitable trusts and not-for-profit incorporated societies.
Schools often lack the skills, equipment, safety management systems, and
experience to deliver outdoor education safely themselves, and
these providers are a critical part of the system.
The way that the concessions framework is currently applied to these
organizations is inconsistent with the purpose of this part of the
act and also with Parliament's original intent when the concessions
regime was introduced through the 1996 Conservation
Amendment Act,
a very similar process to the one that we are in now.
The purpose of the 1996 amendment was to create a consistent and rational
approach for regulating commercial activities and business use on
conservation land. And commercial activities were defined in the legislation
and continue to be defined in the legislation as activities undertaken for
gain or reward, pecuniary or otherwise.
Not-for-profit charitable organizations delivering outdoor education
activities are not commercial businesses.
They do not make a profit, and they do not receive gain or reward
from public conservation land.
We assert that Parliament did not set out to regulate charitable trusts
taking students on their first overnight tramp, yet that is what has
happened. The legislation that is intended to foster
appreciation and enjoyment of New Zealand's wild places is instead making it
harder for young New Zealanders to access, experience, and benefit from
them. And this is something that we believe is
deeply counterproductive.
This committee has the opportunity to correct this through this bill The bill
provides for the minister to classify activities as exempt from the concessions
regime.
We ask the committee to recommend that outdoor education activities undertaken by
not-for-profit outdoor education providers and tertiary institutes
be added to the list of activities that can be carried out without a concession in
Section 14A of the bill. We
also ask that Section 13E explicitly states that the National
Conservation Policy Statement must classify outdoor education activities
undertaken by not-for-profit providers as exempt.
Those two things are required to give clarity and certainty.
We also ask that Section 14A is broadened to make it really clear
that cost recovery charges made by not-for-profit providers
delivering education activities are not gain or reward.
This would prevent these providers from being misclassified, as they
currently are, as businesses simply because they charge to cover gear,
staffing, and instructor costs.
Relying on interpretation or ministerial
discretion alone provides
insufficient long-term certainty for the outdoor education sector.
Clear statutory direction is needed to address this inequity and ensure
young people continue to have opportunities to take part in outdoor
education on public conservation land, regardless of who is running that
activity.
My final point concerns access charging.
We acknowledge the financial pressures facing DOC and the need to supplement vote
conservation with revenue from other sources, including charges for the use of
facilities such as huts and campsites.
We also support the bill's more targeted approach of allowing an access charge to
be levied on international visitors at specified high-use sites.
However, we remain opposed to access charges for New Zealand
residents. Public conservation land should remain freely
accessible, regardless of income or where people live.
Any access charging regime must preserve that principle.
We also strongly support transparent reinvestment of levy revenue.
The public should be able to see how much revenue is collected and where it is
spent, and importantly, what outcomes are achieved from that, including
visitor and recreation outcomes.
So in closing, Recreation Aotearoa supports many
aspects of this bill, including the improvements to planning and
concession processes. But we urge the committee to ensure that these
reforms preserve the longstanding purpose of New Zealand's conservation
system.
We also ask the committee to take this opportunity to address the
longstanding inequity faced by not-for-profit outdoor education providers.
A small legislative change could make a significant difference and ensure
young New Zealanders can continue to access and benefit from outdoor
education on conservation land. Thank you for your time, and I
welcome any questions.
Yeah. Thank you, Sarah. Some really interesting points there, and I think we can
all relate to school camps and how valuable they are in getting our young people
out there.
So Celia, we'll go to you first for a question.
Thank you. Thank you, Chair. Thank you very much for your presentation, and that I
want to focus on that particular use of the not-for-profits getting people
outdoors,
because you
made
points that are different from other submissions.
Mm.
Would you imagine that that would include
not necessarily education providers, but other
non-profits that are trying to get people out into the outdoors?
And I'd give you the examples of Manawatu Walking
Festival, Rotarua Walking Festival, Ruapehu Trail
Fest. All of these places, they use conservation land.
But if you interpret it very strictly,
because the people going on those walks are not members of the
organization, they would face those concession
issues.
Mm.
Possibly even if there wasn't a charge.
Yeah. So our submission pertains specifically to outdoor
education providers, but I think the underlying principle here is that, or the
underlying point that we're seeking to make is that the concessions regime
was never intended as a management tool for managing visitor
impacts. It was intended as a way to regulate business and commercial
use of public land. So
I think
we have fallen into a situation where concessions are used as the
default way to manage visitor use, and we are suggesting that that should not be
the case, was not the original intent.
And for these organizations, particularly not-for-profit outdoor
education providers doing clearly public good activities,
there are better ways to manage
those organizations on public conservation land.
Thank you.
I kind of had a similar question, because
could you give us an example? I just thought it was-
Yeah, sure
... quite an interesting point that you made at the start around obviously the
education providers that are having to pay, and obviously-
Yep
... then others just use the land, and it's free, and it's
easy.
Yep.
Could you kind of put that into a tangible context?
Yeah. So our members include organizations like Hillary Outdoors.
Yeah.
So they were the Sir Edmund Hillary Outdoor Pursuits Centre,
YMCA, Whenua Iti, others around the country.
So they are organizations who schools will essentially
outsource to, to deliver outdoor education for them.
So a school that chooses to
run their own outdoor education program is treated very separately to a school
that
uses a not-for-profit provider to run activities for their
kids.
Mm. Okay, interesting. One last question from Lan.
Yeah, just on the same thing. Can you help us understand, would
the
entirety of the activities that that not-for-profit, for
example,
undertook in conservation land, would they all be exempt,
or would it be for specific activities?
So what we're suggesting is low impact outdoor education activities
like tramping, like rock climbing on established routes,
like kayaking.
Yeah.
Those are the activities. So you get a concession for an activity, not because of
the organization-
Yeah
... type that you are. So those types of activities would be exempt.
We have,
for clarity, said in our submission that we are not proposing
that providers that have physical infrastructure buildings
and permanent structures on conservation land are exempt.
We think that's still
a sensible and practical requirement for those things to be
regulated through the concessions regime.
So what we are talking about is
taking kids out to do activities.
Yeah.
Yeah. Thank you. Interesting. Thank you very much.
We have met time. We appreciate your submission today. So thank you.
And that brings us to the end of our public submissions this
afternoon for today on the Conservation Amendment Bill.
Thank you